<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pcm="http://www.masereeuw.nl/namespaces/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="nl">Isaac Israëls aan Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Amsterdam, 1896 of 1897.</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Isaac Israëls to Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Amsterdam, 1896 or 1897.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name ref="https://huygens.knaw.nl/en">Huygens Institute for the History and Culture of the Netherlands (KNAW)</name>
               <name ref="https://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/en">Van Gogh Museum Amsterdam</name>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-03-12">12 March 2024</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
                  <p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <ptr type="webedition" target="TODO"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>The Netherlands</country>
                  <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                  <institution>VGM</institution>
                  <idno>b8583V2008</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="ii">
                     <idno>035</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="letter"/>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers141">Isaac Israëls</rs>
               <date notBefore="1896" notAfter="1897" cert="low"/>
               <placeName>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers140">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface n="1r" xml:id="s1r">
         <graphic url="b8583V2008r_b"/>
         <zone n="1r1"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r1"/>
         <zone n="1r4"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r4"/>
      </surface>
      <surface n="1v" xml:id="s1v">
         <graphic url="b8583V2008v_vs_b"/>
         <zone n="1v2"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v2"/>
         <zone n="1v3"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v3"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body divRole="original-translation">
         <div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
            <pb xml:id="pb.orig.nl.1" f="1r" facs="#z1r1" n="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Amst.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.2" n="2">Vrijdagavond</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Lieve Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.4" n="4">Ik had onze conversatie nog wel willen rekken, maar ’t kwam mij voor dat je ’t beter vond dat ik er maar vandoor ging, en ik moest ook vroeg hier zijn.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">Was ’t wel goed dat ik kwam? Je was net al goed op streek om me te vergeten geloof ik? Is ’t niet?</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">Laat ik je dit nog even zeggen: de reden dat ik je in zoolang niet kon hebben is hoofdzakelijk dat ik een beetje ongesteld was.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.a"/> Dat is nu over. En dan het werk, dat is een engrenage,<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.b"/> dat weet je zoo niet.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">Ik vind ’t volstrekt niet goed dat we elkaar zoo weinig zien, zooals je denkt geloof ik. Veel liever zou ik <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> willen dat we een vaste dag afspraken, eens in de week bijvoorbeeld, overdag of ’s avonds? </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">– Maar ’t is waar: je hebt nu ernstige gemoedsbezwaren en je hebt altijd zoo’n tweestrijd.–</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.9" n="9" rend="indent">My dear, laat ik je nu nog eens eerlijk zeggen waar ’t op staat.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.10" n="10" rend="indent">Ik hou heusch <hi rend="italics">heel</hi> veel van je (daar, ben je nu tevreden) en ik ben heel blij met je vriendschap. Denk je nu niet dat ik ’t ook naar vind dat je daar zoo dikwijls verdriet en angst mee hebt.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.11" n="11" rend="indent">Ik vind het heusch soms beroerd, dan voel ik mijzelf schuldig want ik heb innerlijk ook schuld, zeg maar niet van nee.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.12" n="12" rend="indent">Ik moest ’t niet prettig vinden om je als vriendin te willen houden, <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> terwijl ik weet dat ik niet doen kan wat jij ’t liefst zou willen. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.13" n="13" rend="indent">Het is misschien een goed moment voor je om er nogeens goed over te denken wat nu heusch voor jou ’t beste is. Denk er eens driedubbel en dwars over na, neem dan een kloek besluit en hou je er bij.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.14" n="14" rend="indent">Óf – schik je naar de stem van ’t geweten, familie en traditie. Vertel hun altijd alles wat je op je hartje hebt (wat een bedorven kindje om dat nu zoo heerlijk te vinden).</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.15" n="15" rend="indent">Óf – je weet wel.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.16" n="16" rend="indent">Heusch, doe het nú want nu is het oogenblik daar dat de <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r4" n="4"/> familiegolf je weer moet verzwelgen – óf ik heb er nooit geen gevoel meer voor, dat voel ik aankomen. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.17" n="17" rend="indent">Ik neem het ernstig, Jo, denk na, overweeg rijpelijk.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.18" n="18" rend="indent">Ik zal mij houden aan wat jij ’t beste vindt, maar hou jij je der dan ook aan, als ’t kan. (Dat laatste zinnetje had ik niet moeten zeggen. Dat is te veel à la jou, “als ’t kan”). Laten we nu, of liever jij nu, decideren: of ’t is er geweest, of ’t moet op ruimer en uitgebreider schaal worden voortgezet. (Excuseer deze slechte beeldspraak.)</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.19" n="19" rend="indent">Vaarwel of tot ziens,</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.20" n="20">Yours</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.21" n="21">Isaac</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
            <pb xml:id="pb.tr.en.1"
                corresp="#pb.orig.nl.1"
                f="1r"
                facs="#z1r1"
                n="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.1" corresp="#p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Amst.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.2" corresp="#p.orig.nl.2" n="2">Friday evening</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.3" corresp="#p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Dearest Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.4" corresp="#p.orig.nl.4" n="4">I had wanted to spin out our conversation, but it occurred to me that you thought it would be better if I just went, and I had to be here early anyway.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.5" corresp="#p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">Was it all right for me to come? You were already well on the way to forgetting me, I think? Weren’t you?</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.6" corresp="#p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">Let me just say this: the reason I couldn’t have you for such a long time is mainly that I didn’t feel very well. That’s over. And then the work, that’s a complicated business, <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.a"/> you don’t know that.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.7" corresp="#p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">I think it’s not good at all that we see one another so little, as you think, I believe. I would much prefer it <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> if we could agree on a set day, once a week for instance, during the day or in the evening.  </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.8" corresp="#p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">– But it’s true that you now have a seriously guilty conscience and that you’ve always been in such a dilemma.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.9" corresp="#p.orig.nl.9" n="9" rend="indent">My dear, let me say once again honestly what the situation is.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.10"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.10"
               n="10"
               rend="indent">I really love you <hi rend="italics">very</hi> much (there, are you happy now?) and I’m very happy with your friendship. Please don’t doubt that I hate the fact that you are so often sad and fearful.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.11"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.11"
               n="11"
               rend="indent">I sometimes get upset about it, and then I feel guilty myself because inwardly I have guilt, too. Please don’t say no.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.12"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.12"
               n="12"
               rend="indent">I shouldn’t enjoy keeping you as my friend <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> whilst knowing that I can’t do what you would prefer.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.13"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.13"
               n="13"
               rend="indent">Perhaps this is the right moment for you to think hard about what’s really best for you. Think about it very carefully, then take a bold decision and keep to it.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.14"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.14"
               n="14"
               rend="indent">Either comply with the voice of your conscience, family and tradition. Always tell them everything that’s on your mind (what a spoilt child to find that so comforting).</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.15"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.15"
               n="15"
               rend="indent">Or – you know very well.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.16"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.16"
               n="16"
               rend="indent">Do it now because now is the moment that the <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r4" n="4"/> family will engulf you again. Or – I’ll never have no feelings about it. I can sense that’s coming.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.17"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.17"
               n="17"
               rend="indent">I’m taking this seriously, Jo, think carefully, ponder profoundly.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.18"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.18"
               n="18"
               rend="indent">I shall abide by what you think is best, but you must also abide by it, if possible. (I shouldn’t have written that last phrase). It’s too much à la you to say ‘if possible’. So let us, or rather you, decide now whether it’s over, or it should be continued on a wider and more comprehensive scale. (Please excuse this poor metaphor).</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.19"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.19"
               n="19"
               rend="indent">Farewell or see you soon,</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.20" corresp="#p.orig.nl.20" n="20">Yours</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.21" corresp="#p.orig.nl.21" n="21">Isaac</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note xml:id="note.d433e4635" type="dating">
            <p>De brief is moeilijk precies te dateren. Aangezien er sprake is van relationele gemoedsbezwaren bij Jo, en Israëls opmerkt dat ze ‘net al goed op streek’ was om hem te vergeten, moet dit schrijven dateren van ergens in 1896 of 1897, toen hun verhouding bij tijden flink in beroering was.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note xml:id="note.d433e4719" type="dating">
            <p>The letter is difficult to date precisely. Given the reference to scruples about their relationship on Jo’s part, and Israëls’s remark that she was ‘already well on the way’ to forgetting him, this letter must date from some time in 1896 or 1897, when their relationship was in considerable turmoil at times.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="langnotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="a" xml:id="note.orig.nl.a">
            <p>Dat ik me niet zo lekker voelde.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="b" xml:id="note.orig.nl.b">
            <p>Raderwerk, ingewikkelde organisatie.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="langnotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note n="a" xml:id="note.tr.en.a">
            <p>Israëls uses the French slang word <hi rend="italics">engrenage</hi>.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
