<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pcm="http://www.masereeuw.nl/namespaces/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="nl">Isaac Israëls aan Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Goes, 2 oktober 1897.</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Isaac Israëls to Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Goes, 2 October 1897.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name ref="https://huygens.knaw.nl/en">Huygens Institute for the History and Culture of the Netherlands (KNAW)</name>
               <name ref="https://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/en">Van Gogh Museum Amsterdam</name>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-03-12">12 March 2024</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
                  <p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <ptr type="webedition" target="TODO"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>The Netherlands</country>
                  <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                  <institution>VGM</institution>
                  <idno>b8618V2008</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="ii">
                     <idno>048</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="letter"/>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers141">Isaac Israëls</rs>
               <date when="1897-10-02"/>
               <placeName>Goes, The Netherlands</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers140">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface n="1r" xml:id="s1r">
         <graphic url="b8618V2008r_b"/>
      </surface>
      <surface n="1v" xml:id="s1v">
         <graphic url="b8618V2008v_vs_b"/>
         <zone n="1v2"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v2"/>
         <zone n="1v3"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v3"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body divRole="original-translation">
         <div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
            <pb xml:id="pb.orig.nl.1" f="1r" facs="#s1r" n="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.1" n="1">
               <hi rend="italics">Goes</hi>, 2 october [ <hi rend="italics">189</hi>]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.2" n="2">Lieve Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Ik schrijf je nu maar vast want dan krijg je hem op je verjaardag.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.1"/> Ik ben nu weer hier maar in een ander hotelletje zooals je hierboven wel zien zult.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.2"/> Schrijf mij eens even hoe het met je gaat en of je je nogal goed voelt? Ik ben een paar dagen in Oostburg<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.3"/> geweest maar nu weer hier terug om nog wat te doen zoolang het weer zoo goed blijft. Hoe is het en heb je nu weer nieuwe logees en is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Anna Vis</rs> nog bij je?<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.4"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.4" n="4" rend="indent">Het is hier maar kalm, maar ik kan hier nogal werken, het is jammer dat je mij niet eens komt opzoeken in mijn “salon”, dat is de mooie kamer hier waar ik huis.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">
               <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> Wat is de mensch? Niet veel bizonders als je er goed over nadenkt. Ik geloof dat ’t mij wel bevallen zou om geen vast domicilie te hebben, alleen ’t is duur. Enfin, ik heb hier een leesbibliotheek ontdekt, voor 5 cent in de week kan je daar de mooiste boeken krijgen. <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.5"/> Dus ik ben gered. Dan ga ik maar heel vroeg na bed en dan sta ik maar vroeg op, dat is ’t beste. Ik kom hier ook bij families in huis, met bloote armen en groote mutsen op, dat spreekt. Maar dat kost ook geld.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.6"/> Wie had gedacht dat ik nogeens zoolang in Zeeland zou zitten, maar ik ken de Munt wel en de Kalverstraat. <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.7"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">– Ben je die Russen niet gaan hooren in Amsterdam?<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.8"/> Nee, dat is jammer want dat is wel mooi. Het is anders wel vreemd hoe de mensch zich kan schikken <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> in ’t gemis van de genietingen der beschaving, illustraties,<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.9"/> drukke straten, trems, fersoenlijke<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.a"/> kennissen enz. Je groet hier anders in een uur meer als in Amsterdam in een jaar want dat gaat hier maar makkelijk. Welnu, het zal mij overigens plezier doen als ik je eens weer zie maar ik zou ’t toch heel lief van je vinden als je maar ’s avonds eens kwam een enkele keer als ik weer in A. ben. Ik blijf nu nog zoowat een week hier dus ik hoor wel wat van je?</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">Intusschen veel plezier op je verjaardag hoor, Jopie.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">Dag.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.9" n="9">Yours</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.10" n="10">Isaac</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
            <pb xml:id="pb.tr.en.1"
                corresp="#pb.orig.nl.1"
                f="1r"
                facs="#s1r"
                n="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.1" corresp="#p.orig.nl.1" n="1">
               <hi rend="italics">Goes, </hi>2 October [ <hi rend="italics">189</hi>]</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.2" corresp="#p.orig.nl.2" n="2">My dear Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.3" corresp="#p.orig.nl.3" n="3">I’m writing to you now because then you will get it on your birthday.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.1"/> I’m here again, but now in a different hotel as you can see above.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.2"/> Write and let me know how you are doing and if you feel quite all right? I’ve been in Oostburg for a few days,<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.3"/> but I’m back here now to do something as long as the weather stays so good. How are you and do you have new guests again and is <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Anna Vis</rs> still with you?<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.4"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.4" corresp="#p.orig.nl.4" n="4" rend="indent">It’s quiet, but I can get work done here, it’s a shame you don’t come and visit me in my “salon”, that’s the fine room where I’m staying here.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.5" corresp="#p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">
               <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> What is man? Nothing very special if you really think about it. I believe it would suit me not to have a fixed abode, only it’s expensive. Anyway, I’ve discovered a lending library here; you can get the best books there for 5 cents a week. <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.5"/> So I’m saved. I go to bed very early and then I get up early, that’s best. I also visit families at home, with bare arms, wearing large caps, that’s appealing. But that costs money, too.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.6"/> Who would have thought that I would stay so long in Zeeland again, but I already know the Mint and Kalverstraat.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.7"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.6" corresp="#p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">– Didn’t you go and listen to the Russians in Amsterdam?<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.8"/> No, that’s a pity because it is good. It’s strange how people can resign themselves <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> to the absence of the pleasures of civilization, illustrations, <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.9"/> busy streets, trams, respectable acquaintances etc. You greet more people here in an hour than you do in a year in Amsterdam, because it’s very easy-going here. Well then, I will be very pleased to see you again but I would think it very sweet of you if you just came one evening when I’m back in A. I shall be staying here for another week or so, so will I hear something from you here?</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.7" corresp="#p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">Meanwhile, you have a very happy birthday, Jopie.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.8" corresp="#p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">Bye.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.9" corresp="#p.orig.nl.9" n="9">Yours</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.10" corresp="#p.orig.nl.10" n="10">Isaac</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note xml:id="note.d433e6624" type="dating">
            <p>Israëls schrijf wel de datum maar niet het jaar boven de brief. Aangezien hij informeert of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Anna Vis</rs> nog bij Jo is en zij in de maand oktober van het jaar 1897 enkele keren logies betaalde, is de onderhavige brief op 2 oktober 1897 gedateerd. Zie <ref target="bibliolist-nl.xml#bg012">
                  <hi rend="italics">Account Book</hi> 2002</ref>, p. 113 en 161. Voorgedrukt briefhoofd: ‘Hôtel Zoutkeet. <hi rend="blockletter">s. verwer, goes</hi>. / <hi rend="italics">Goes, ….. 189..</hi>’</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note xml:id="note.d433e6793" type="dating">
            <p>Israëls wrote the date but not the year at the top of the letter. Since he asks whether <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Anna Vis</rs> is still with Jo and she paid for rooms several times in the month of October in the year 1897, the present letter has been dated 2 October 1897. See <ref target="bibliolist-en.xml#bg012">
                  <hi rend="italics">Account Book</hi> 2002</ref>, pp. 113 and 161. Printed letterhead: ‘Hôtel Zoutkeet. <hi rend="blockletter">s. verwer, goes</hi>. / <hi rend="italics">Goes, ….. 189..</hi>’</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.orig.nl.1">
            <p>Jo was op 4 oktober jarig – ze werd 35 jaar.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.orig.nl.2">
            <p>Israëls moet Jo dus al eerder vanuit Goes hebben geschreven. Het briefpapier waarop hij deze brief schrijft is dat van Hotel <hi rend="italics">Zoutkeet</hi> op de Grote Markt. Sinds 1890 was <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers138">Sijbrandus Verwer</rs> daarvan de eigenaar. Hotel Zoutkeet in Goes, circa 1890. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii028"/>
            </p>
         </note>
         <note n="3" xml:id="note.orig.nl.3">
            <p>Oostburg in Zeeuws-Vlaanderen.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="4" xml:id="note.orig.nl.4">
            <p>Op dat moment waren bij Jo in Bussum geen nieuwe pensiongasten. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Anna Cornelia Vis</rs> had van 1882-1886 de Rijksakademie in Amsterdam gevolgd en vertrok daarna naar Parijs. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Vis</rs> kende verschillende Tachtigers en raakte bevriend met de kunstenares <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers114">Sara de Swart</rs>. Zie Jaap Versteegh, <hi rend="italics">Fatale kunst. Leven en werk van Sara de Swart (1861-1951)</hi>. Nijmegen 2016, p. 43 en 65-77. Jo kende <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Vis</rs> al langer – ze hadden elkaar in 1892 ontmoet bij <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers067">Jan Veth</rs>. Zie <ref target="bibliolist-nl.xml#bg013">
                  <hi rend="italics">Dagboek</hi>
               </ref> 4, p. 17. Op 15 oktober 1897 betaalde <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Vis</rs> Jo voor de laatste keer als pensiongast in villa Helma.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="5" xml:id="note.orig.nl.5">
            <p>Dit was de leesbibliotheek ‘Nut en Uitspanning’. Zie John Helsloot, <hi rend="italics">Vermaak tussen beschaving en kerstening. Goes 1867-1896</hi>. Amsterdam 1995, p. 56-59. Met dank aan Frank de Klerk, Archivist Gemeente Goes.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="6" xml:id="note.orig.nl.6">
            <p> Israëls portretteerde de Zeeuwen bij hen thuis. Vgl. voor de klederdracht aan het eind van de negentiende eeuw dit dubbelportret: Vrouw en meisje in Zuid-Bevelandse klederdracht, ongedateerd. Fotograaf J.J. Quist. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii029"/>
            </p>
         </note>
         <note n="7" xml:id="note.orig.nl.7">
            <p>Een bekend plein en een bekende winkelstraat in Amsterdam.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="8" xml:id="note.orig.nl.8">
            <p>In september 1897 was een Russisch gemengd gezelschap van veertig zangers onder leiding van <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers099">Nadina Slaviansky</rs> op tournee door Nederland. Op het programma stonden Russische en Slavische liederen. Talrijke kranten plaatsten advertenties en gaven besprekingen van het concert.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="9" xml:id="note.orig.nl.9">
            <p>Geïllustreerde tijdschriften, of reproductiegrafiek.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="en">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.tr.en.1">
            <p>Jo turned thirty-five on 4 October.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.tr.en.2">
            <p>Israëls must already have written to Jo from Goes before this. The notepaper on which he wrote this letter came from Hotel Zoutkeet in the Grote Markt. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers138">Sijbrandus Verwer</rs> had owned it since 1890. Hotel Zoutkeet in Goes, c. 1890. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii028"/>
            </p>
         </note>
         <note n="3" xml:id="note.tr.en.3">
            <p>Oostburg in Zeeuws-Vlaanderen.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="4" xml:id="note.tr.en.4">
            <p>At that moment there were no new guests in Jo’s boarding house in Bussum. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Anna Cornelia Vis</rs> had studied at the Rijksakademie in Amsterdam from 1882 to 1886 and then went to Paris. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Vis</rs> knew several Tachtigers and became friendly with the artist <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers114">Sara de Swart</rs>. See Jaap Versteegh, <hi rend="italics">Fatale kunst. Leven en werk van Sara de Swart (1861-1951)</hi>. Nijmegen 2016, pp. 43 and 65-77. Jo had known <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Vis</rs> for some time – they had met at <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers067">Jan Veth</rs>’s in 1892. See <ref target="bibliolist-en.xml#bg013">
                  <hi rend="italics">Diary</hi>
               </ref> 4, p. 17. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers006">Vis</rs> paid Jo as a boarder in Villa Helma for the last time on 15 October 1897.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="5" xml:id="note.tr.en.5">
            <p>This was the library ‘Nut en Uitspanning’. See John Helsloot, <hi rend="italics">Vermaak tussen beschaving en kerstening. Goes 1867-1896</hi>. Amsterdam 1995, pp. 56-59. With thanks to Frank de Klerk, Goes council archivist.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="6" xml:id="note.tr.en.6">
            <p> Israëls portrayed the Zeelanders in their homes. Cf. this double portrait for the traditional costume at the end of the nineteenth century: Woman and girl in the costume of South Beveland, undated. Photograph J.J. Quist. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii029"/>
            </p>
         </note>
         <note n="7" xml:id="note.tr.en.7">
            <p>A well-known square and shopping street in Amsterdam.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="8" xml:id="note.tr.en.8">
            <p>In September 1897 a Russian company of forty singers led by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers099">Nadina Slaviansky</rs> went on tour through the Netherlands. The programme included Russian and Slavic songs. Numerous newspapers ran advertisements and printed reviews of the concert.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="9" xml:id="note.tr.en.9">
            <p>Illustrated magazines, or reproductive prints.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="langnotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="a" xml:id="note.orig.nl.a">
            <p>Deze platte vormvariant van ‘fatsoenlijk’ werd vaker als een geintje zo gespeld: ‘Al bin ik maar een keukemeid ik bin toch een fersoenlijk burgermans kind’, aldus het <hi rend="italics">Algemeen Handelsblad</hi>, 21 juni 1883.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
