<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pcm="http://www.masereeuw.nl/namespaces/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="nl">Isaac Israëls aan Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Solo (Surakarta, Java), 6 juli 1922.</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Isaac Israëls to Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Solo (Surakarta, Java), 6 July 1922.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name ref="https://huygens.knaw.nl/en">Huygens Institute for the History and Culture of the Netherlands (KNAW)</name>
               <name ref="https://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/en">Van Gogh Museum Amsterdam</name>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-03-12">12 March 2024</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
                  <p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <ptr type="webedition" target="TODO"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>The Netherlands</country>
                  <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                  <institution>VGM</institution>
                  <idno>b8648V2008</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="ii">
                     <idno>098</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="letter"/>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers141">Isaac Israëls</rs>
               <date when="1922-07-06"/>
               <placeName>Solo, Dutch East Indies</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers140">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface n="1r" xml:id="s1r">
         <graphic url="b8648V2008r_b"/>
         <zone n="1r1"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r1"/>
         <zone n="1r4"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r4"/>
      </surface>
      <surface n="1v" xml:id="s1v">
         <graphic url="b8648V2008v_vs_b"/>
         <zone n="1v2"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v2"/>
         <zone n="1v3"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v3"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body divRole="original-translation">
         <div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
            <pb xml:id="pb.orig.nl.1" f="1r" facs="#z1r1" n="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Solo</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.2" n="2">6 juli</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Beste Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.4" n="4">Zeker ontvang je tegelijk met deze een brief van <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">Mevr. de Vries</rs>, zij is hier al een tijdje op Java geweest en wil nu graag over Amerika terug,<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.1"/> zij kent daar echter niemand en nu had ik gedacht dat jij haar misschien kunt introduceeren bij enkele kennissen die je geschikt acht.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.2"/> Het zou voor haar een enorm verschil zijn natuurlijk, <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> of zij daar aardige menschen kent, want het moet dunkt mij ontzettend zijn om daar heelemaal alleen te zijn. Ik hoop dus dat je het kunt doen en dat er nog tijd voor is, misschien als je dadelijk schrijft zij er nog wat aan heeft (maar laten je  <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers119 bio.xml#pers072">kleinkindertjes</rs> je tijd??????).<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.3"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">Ik zou ook wel lust hebben die reis te maken maar ik ben hier nog lang niet klaar en voor iemand die hier niet veel te doen heeft is ’t van een verveling waar je je geen voorstelling van kunt maken, <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> ’t is dus maar ’t beste dat zij maar vast gaat. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">– Ik heb nog steeds geen apen gezien, jij sprak van oerwouden, maar mijn lieve menschje, die <hi rend="italics">zijn</hi> er op Java niet!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">Ja wel in een paar uithoeken nog wel, en zoo’n enkel oerboschje, maar <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> zelfs geloof ik niet meer. Je weet toch dat Java het dichtst bevolkte land van de wereld is? Ofschoon ik verre van enthousiast ben over dit land vind ik één ding toch heerlijk: het klimaat! Nooit hoef je te vragen ’s ochtends wat voor weer het is. Altijd heerlijk zonnig <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r4" n="4"/> en tot 8 uur (je staat per sé om 6 uur op) heerlijk koel. Nooit haast wind, het begrip “winderig” bestaat hier niet!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">Ik <hi rend="italics">denk</hi> dat ik 6 Sept. per Joh. de Witt terugkom<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.4"/> aangezien <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers027 bio.xml#pers115">de Delprats</rs>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.5"/> er ook mee terugkomen. Wat <hi rend="italics">zal</hi> ik een spijt hebben dat ik niet hier gebleven ben als ik eenmaal weer in Holland zit, dat weet ik <hi rend="italics">nu</hi> al maar – men <hi rend="italics">blijft</hi> hier nu eenmaal niet!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.9" n="9" rend="indent">Blijf ik toch event. nog langer hier dan hoor je ’t natuurlijk wel. Ik hoop in dien tijd nog wat van je te hooren, hierop antwoorden zal wel niet goed gaan meer!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.10" n="10" rend="indent">Hartelijke groeten ook aan <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">V.</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">J.</rs>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.6"/> van</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.11" n="11">Je</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.12" n="12">Isaac</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
            <pb xml:id="pb.tr.en.1"
                corresp="#pb.orig.nl.1"
                f="1r"
                facs="#z1r1"
                n="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.1" corresp="#p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Solo</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.2" corresp="#p.orig.nl.2" n="2">6 July</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.3" corresp="#p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Dear Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.4" corresp="#p.orig.nl.4" n="4">I’m sure you’ll receive at the same time as this a letter from <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">Mrs de Vries</rs>; she’s been here on Java for a while and now wants to go back by way of America,<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.1"/> however she doesn’t know anyone there and now I thought that perhaps you could introduce her to a few acquaintances you consider suitable.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.2"/> It would make a huge difference to her, of course, <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> if she knew nice people there, for it seems to me that it must be awful to be there all alone. So I hope that you can do it and that there’s still time for it, perhaps if you write immediately, she will get some benefit (but do your darling  <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers119 bio.xml#pers072">grandchildren</rs> give you any time for yourself??????).<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.3"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.5" corresp="#p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">I would also like to make the trip but I’m still very far from finished here, and for someone who hasn’t got much to do here it’s more boring than you can imagine, so <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> it’s best that she goes. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.6" corresp="#p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">– I still haven’t seen any monkeys; you talk about jungles, but my dear girl there <hi rend="italics">aren’t</hi> any on Java!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.7" corresp="#p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">Well there still are in a few remote corners, and the occasional primaeval forest, but I don’t even believe <hi rend="italics">that</hi> any more. You do know that Java is the most densely populated country in the world? Although I am far from enthusiastic about this country, there is one thing I find delightful: the climate! You never have to ask yourself in the morning what the weather’s like. Always delightfully sunny <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r4" n="4"/> and until 8 o’clock (you get up at 6 o’clock for sure) delightfully cool. Hardly ever any wind; the concept ‘windy’ doesn’t exist here! </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.8" corresp="#p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">I <hi rend="italics">think</hi> I’ll come back by the Joh. de Witt on 6 Sept,<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.4"/> since <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers027 bio.xml#pers115">the Delprats</rs>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.5"/> are also embarking on that ship. How sorry I  <hi rend="italics">shall</hi> be that I didn’t stay here once I’m back in Holland, I already know that <hi rend="italics">now</hi> – one just doesn’t <hi rend="italics">stay</hi> here!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.9" corresp="#p.orig.nl.9" n="9" rend="indent">If I do stay longer here after all, of course I’ll let you know. I hope I still hear from you in that time, answering this won’t be any good now!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.10"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.10"
               n="10"
               rend="indent">Warm wishes also to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">V.</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">J.</rs>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.6"/> from</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.11" corresp="#p.orig.nl.11" n="11">Your</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.12" corresp="#p.orig.nl.12" n="12">Isaac</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note xml:id="note.d433e16602" type="dating">
            <p>Briefhoofd: ‘6 juli’. Israëls spreekt over zijn terugkeer naar Nederland – dat was in 1922.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note xml:id="note.d433e16796" type="dating">
            <p>Letter headed: ‘6 July’. Israëls mentions his return to the Netherlands – that was in 1922.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.orig.nl.1">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">Sophie de Vries-Dalberg</rs>, een maîtresse van Israëls. Zij was in april 1922 op Java aangekomen, verbleef enige tijd samen met Israëls in Indonesië en reisde daarna door naar Amerika, waar ze in september aankwam. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">De Vries</rs> was van plan via New York weer terug te keren naar Nederland. Isaac Israëls aan Marie Witsen-Schorr, 27 april 1922 en Isaac Israëls aan Willem Witsen en Marie Witsen-Schorr, 5 juni 1922 en 6 september 1922. <hi rend="italics">KBH</hi> 75 C 51.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">Sophie de Vries</rs> was in 1911 gescheiden van haar man <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers113">Samuel de Vries</rs>. Ze zat talrijke keren model voor Israëls. Zschrie <ref target="bibliolist-nl.xml#bg030">Tent.cat. Amsterdam 2012</ref>, p. 26-27. Vgl. ook brief <ref target="ii092.xml">092</ref>. Een brief van haar aan Jo is niet bekend. Omstreeks 1930 schilderde Israëls op paneel aan elke zijde een portret van <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">De Vries</rs> en hemzelf (privécollectie). Zie <ref target="bibliolist-nl.xml#bg025">J.H. Reisel, <hi rend="italics">Isaac Israëls. Portret van een Hollandse impressionist</hi>. Amsterdam 1967</ref>, p. 118. Vgl. het eveneens tweezijdig beschilderde paneel met hun beider portretten: Isaac Israëls,  <hi rend="italics">Zelfportret in het atelier</hi> (voorkant) en <hi rend="italics">Portret van Sophie de Vries-Dalberg</hi> (achterkant), ongedateerd. Verblijfplaats onbekend. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii045"/> en <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii046"/> Geveild bij Christie’s in Amsterdam op 28 oktober 2003 (lot 179).</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.orig.nl.2">
            <p>Jo had tussen augustus 1916 en april 1919 in New York gewoond, waar ze verschillende kennissen had.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="3" xml:id="note.orig.nl.3">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers119">Theo van Gogh</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers072">Johan van Gogh</rs>, over wie ze Israëls had bericht; vgl. brief <ref target="ii097.xml">097</ref>. Voor Jo waren haar kleinkinderen een grote troost in de laatste fase van haar leven. In de zomer logeerden zij langere tijd bij haar in Laren: ‘Ik heb er zoo van genoten,’ schreef ze aan <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers009">Annie van Gelder-Pigeaud</rs>, ‘want hier in de stad is het toch altijd maar een uurtje dat ik ze zie, elken dag.’ Over haar kleinkinderen berichtte Jo eveneens aan <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers103">Paul Gachet</rs>. VGM, b1519; 24 april 1922 – en aan <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers009">Annie van Gelder-Pigeaud</rs>. VGM, b3721; 3 oktober 1922.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="4" xml:id="note.orig.nl.4">
            <p>Het stoomschip Johan de Witt van de ‘Stoomvaart Maatschappij Nederland’. Israëls zou uiteindelijk in november 1922 terugreizen van Batavia naar Amsterdam met het stoomschip Vondel.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="5" xml:id="note.orig.nl.5">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers027">Mr. Daniël Apollonius Delprat</rs> was getrouwd met <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers115">Saskia Veth</rs>, de dochter van <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers067">Jan</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers007">Anna Veth-Dirks</rs>. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers027">Delprat</rs> was van 1920 tot 1926 tweede vertegenwoordiger van de ‘Stoomvaart Maatschappij Nederland’ in Nederlands-Indië, en van 1921 tot 1927 lid van de ‘Volksraad van Nederlandsch-Indië’. De dertig leden van die Raad werden voor een deel gekozen en voor een deel aangesteld door het koloniaal bestuur. De Volksraad bezat alleen het adviesrecht.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="6" xml:id="note.orig.nl.6">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">Josina</rs>.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="en">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.tr.en.1">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">Sophie de Vries-Dalberg</rs>, Israëls’s mistress. She arrived on Java in April 1922, stayed with Israëls in Indonesia for some time and then travelled on to America, where she arrived in September. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">De Vries</rs> planned to return to the Netherlands via New York. Isaac Israëls to Marie Witsen-Schorr, 27 April 1922 and Isaac Israëls to Willem Witsen and Marie Witsen-Schorr, 5 June 1922 and 6 September 1922. <hi rend="italics">KBH</hi> 75 C 51.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">Sophie de Vries</rs> was divorced from her husband <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers113">Samuel de Vries</rs> in 1911. She sat for Israëls numerous times. See <ref target="bibliolist-en.xml#bg030">exh. cat. Amsterdam 2012</ref>, pp. 26-27. Cf. also letter <ref target="ii092.xml">092</ref>. We know of no letter from her to Jo. Around 1930 Israëls painted a portrait of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers117">De Vries</rs> and himself on each side of a panel (private collection). See J.H. <ref target="bibliolist-en.xml#bg025">Reisel, <hi rend="italics">Isaac Israëls. Portr</hi>
                  <hi rend="italics">e</hi>
                  <hi rend="italics">t van een Hollandse impressionist</hi>. Amsterdam 1967</ref>, p. 118. Cf. the likewise two-sided panel with their portraits: Isaac Israëls,  <hi rend="italics">Self-Portrait in the Studio</hi> (front) and <hi rend="italics">Portrait of Sophie de Vries-Dalberg</hi> (back), undated. Whereabouts unknown. <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii045"/> and <rs type="artwork" ref="artwork.xml#ii046"/> Auctioned at Christie’s in Amsterdam on 28 October 2003 (lot 179).</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.tr.en.2">
            <p>Jo had lived in New York between August 1916 and April 1919, and had many acquaintances there.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="3" xml:id="note.tr.en.3">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers119">Theo van Gogh</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers072">Johan van Gogh</rs>, whom she had told Israëls about; cf. letter <ref target="ii097.xml">097</ref>. Jo’s grandchildren were a great comfort to her in the last phase of her life. In the summer they stayed with her in Laren for some time: ‘I enjoyed it so much,’ she wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers009">Annie van Gelder-Pigeaud</rs>, ‘for here in the city I only ever see them for less than an hour every day.’ Jo also wrote to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers103">Paul Gachet</rs> about her grandchildren. VGM, b1519; 24 April 1922 – and to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers009">Annie van Gelder-Pigeaud</rs>. VGM, b3721; 3 October 1922.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="4" xml:id="note.tr.en.4">
            <p>The steamship <hi rend="italics">Johan de Witt</hi> of the Stoomvaart Maatschappij Nederland. Israëls would eventually travel back from Batavia to Amsterdam on the steamship <hi rend="italics">Vondel</hi> in November 1922.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="5" xml:id="note.tr.en.5">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers027">Daniel Apollonius Delprat</rs> was married to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers115">Saskia Veth</rs>, the daughter of <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers067">Jan</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers007">Anna Veth-Dirks</rs>. From 1920 to 1926 <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers027">Delprat</rs> was the second representative of the Stoomvaart Maatschappij Nederland in the Dutch East Indies, and from 1921 to 1927 a member of the Volksraad van Nederlandsch-Indië (people’s assembly for the East Indies). Some of the thirty members of this council were elected and some appointed by the colonial authorities. The Volksraad only had advisory powers.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="6" xml:id="note.tr.en.6">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">Josina</rs>.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
