<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="md"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pcm="http://www.masereeuw.nl/namespaces/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="nl">Isaac Israëls aan Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Amsterdam, 16 december 1894.</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Isaac Israëls to Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Amsterdam, 16 December 1894.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name ref="https://huygens.knaw.nl/en">Huygens Institute for the History and Culture of the Netherlands (KNAW)</name>
               <name ref="https://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/en">Van Gogh Museum Amsterdam</name>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
            <date when="2999-12-31">TODO date</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <licence target="dummy">
                  <p>Dummy</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <ptr type="webedition" target="TODO"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>The Netherlands</country>
                  <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                  <institution>VGM</institution>
                  <idno>b8565V2008</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="ii">
                     <idno>008</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="letter"/>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers141">Isaac Israëls</rs>
               <date when="1894-12-16"/>
               <placeName>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers140">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface n="1r" xml:id="s1r">
         <zone n="1r1"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r1"/>
         <zone n="1r2"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r2"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body divRole="original-translation">
         <div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
            <pb xml:id="pb.orig.nl.1" f="1r" facs="#z1r1" n="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Amst.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.2" n="2">16 Dec.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Beste Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.4" n="4">Hiernevens de almanak en de boeken.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.1"/> Waarom wou je absoluut niet dat ik En ménage meenam?<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.2"/> Ik heb er veel plezier in gehad ’t nog eens over te lezen. Het speet mij wel eenigzins dat je niet kon komen, daar wij het zoo wat afgesproken hadden, en een ander keer als jij weer wilt kan ik misschien weer niet want ik ben van plan om ’s avonds te gaan werken. Enfin, je moet altijd maar doen wat je denkt dat ’t beste is, dat doe ik ook, maar <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r2" n="2"/> die scrupules van je begrijp ik wel.– </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">Ik dank je nog wel voor je vriendelijke ontvangst en hoop dat ik je niet te veel verveeld heb laatst.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">Steeds,</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.7" n="7">T.t.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.8" n="8">I</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
            <pb xml:id="pb.tr.en.1"
                corresp="#pb.orig.nl.1"
                f="1r"
                facs="#z1r1"
                n="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.1" corresp="#p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Amst.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.2" corresp="#p.orig.nl.2" n="2">16 Dec.</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.3" corresp="#p.orig.nl.3" n="3">Dear Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.4" corresp="#p.orig.nl.4" n="4">Hereby the almanac and the books.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.1"/> Why did you absolutely not want me to take En ménage?<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.2"/> I really enjoyed reading it again. I’m a little sorry that you couldn’t come, since we had more or less agreed on it, and another time if you want to again, perhaps I won’t be able to because I’m planning to start working in the evenings. You must always do what you think best, that’s what I do, too, but I understand <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r2" n="2"/> those scruples of yours.– </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.5" corresp="#p.orig.nl.5" n="5" rend="indent">I thank you for your friendly welcome and hope that I didn’t annoy you too much the other day.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.6" corresp="#p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">Always,</p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.7" corresp="#p.orig.nl.7" n="7">All yours</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.8" corresp="#p.orig.nl.8" n="8">I</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note xml:id="note.d425e900" type="dating">
            <p>Briefhoofd: ‘16 Dec.’ Israëls is op bezoek geweest bij Jo. De toon is nog niet intiem, dus zal de brief uit 1894 dateren – op 16 december 1895 was er namelijk inmiddels ‘met vuur gespeeld’, aldus Jo in haar dagboek (<ref target="bibliolist-nl.xml#bg013">
                  <hi rend="italics">Dagboek</hi>
               </ref> 4, p. 96). Van een contact in of vóór 1893 – anders dan dat Israëls op 2 februari 1891 een condoleance voor het overlijden van <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers120">Theo van Gogh</rs> stuurde en op 25 februari 1892 in <hi rend="italics">Maatschappij Arti et Amicitiae</hi> de kunstbeschouwing over <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers127">Vincent van Gogh</rs> bijwoonde – zijn geen aanwijzingen.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note xml:id="note.d425e982" type="dating">
            <p>Letter headed: ‘16 Dec.’ Israëls had been to visit Jo. The tone is not yet intimate, so the letter will date from 1894 – on 16 December 1895 they had meanwhile ‘been playing with fire’, according to Jo in her Diary (<ref target="bibliolist-en.xml#bg013">
                  <hi rend="italics">Diary</hi>
               </ref> 4, p. 96). There are no indications of a contact in or before 1893 – except that on 2 February 1891 Israëls had sent a letter of condolence on <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers120">Theo van Gogh</rs>’s death and on 25 February 1892 he attended the art appreciation event about <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers127">Vincent van Gogh</rs> in <hi rend="italics">Maatschappij Arti et Amicitiae</hi>.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.orig.nl.1">
            <p>Het is niet bekend om welke geleende titels het ging.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.orig.nl.2">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers076">Joris-Karl Huysmans</rs>, <hi rend="italics">En ménage</hi> (1881). De reden dat Jo niet wilde dat Israëls het boek meenam, moet te maken hebben met wat ze op 15 mei 1892 in haar dagboek schreef: ‘Nog eens gelezen la ménage van <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers076">Huysmans</rs> – er is geen boek dat me zoo aan ons leven in Parijs herinnert als dat. niet om de hoofdfiguren, goddank, maar wel die kleine bijzonderheden van het huishouden – en dan de stad zelf! Onder het lezen was ’t me soms één ondeelbaar klein oogenblik of ik opeens in ons huisje verplaatst was – of ik <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers120">Theo</rs> de sleutel in de deur hoorde steken – zijn stap op de trap – o dat onbeschrijfelijk pijnlijke van één zoo’n oogenblik. Men kan in één minuut meer lijden dan in dagen of jaren lang! Lieveling, lieveling ik mis je zoo, ik verlang zoo naar je!’ <ref target="bibliolist-nl.xml#bg013">
                  <hi rend="italics">Dagboek</hi>
               </ref> 4, p. 49.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="en">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.tr.en.1">
            <p>We do not know which borrowed titles these were.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.tr.en.2">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers076">Joris-Karl Huysmans</rs>, <hi rend="italics">En ménage</hi> (1881). The reason Jo did not want Israëls to take the book must have had to do with what she wrote in her Diary on 15 May 1892: ‘I’ve read En ménage by <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers076">Huysmans</rs> again – there’s no other book that reminds me so much of our life in Paris as that one, not because of the main characters, thank God, but because of those small details of housekeeping – and the city itself! As I read, it was as if for one infinitesimally tiny moment I was suddenly transported to our little home – as though I heard <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers120">Theo</rs> putting the key in the door – his footstep on the stairs – oh the indescribable pain of one such moment. One can suffer more in one minute than in days or years! Darling, darling I miss you so, I long for you so!’ <ref target="bibliolist-en.xml#bg013">
                  <hi rend="italics">Diary</hi>
               </ref> 4, p. 49.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
