<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/editem-letter.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?editem template="letter" adaptation="md"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pcm="http://www.masereeuw.nl/namespaces/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="nl">Isaac Israëls aan Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Aan boord van het stoomschip Koningin der Nederlanden op de Indische Oceaan, 22 november 1921.</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Isaac Israëls to Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Aboard the steamship <hi rend="italics">Koningin der Nederlanden</hi> on the Indian Ocean, 22 November 1921.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name ref="https://huygens.knaw.nl/en">Huygens Institute for the History and Culture of the Netherlands (KNAW)</name>
               <name ref="https://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/en">Van Gogh Museum Amsterdam</name>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
            <date when="2999-12-31">TODO date</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <licence target="dummy">
                  <p>Dummy</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <ptr type="webedition" target="TODO"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>The Netherlands</country>
                  <settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
                  <institution>VGM</institution>
                  <idno>b8646V2008</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="ii">
                     <idno>096</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="letter"/>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers141">Isaac Israëls</rs>
               <date when="1921-11-22"/>
               <placeName>aboard the steamship  Koningin der Nederlanden on the Indian Ocean </placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers140">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface n="1r" xml:id="s1r">
         <zone n="1r1"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r1"/>
         <zone n="1r4"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1r4"/>
      </surface>
      <surface n="1v" xml:id="s1v">
         <zone n="1v2"
               ulx="0"
               uly="0"
               lrx="50"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v2"/>
         <zone n="1v3"
               ulx="50"
               uly="0"
               lrx="100"
               lry="100"
               xml:id="z1v3"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body divRole="original-translation">
         <div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
            <pb xml:id="pb.orig.nl.1" f="1r" facs="#z1r1" n="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Dinsdag <hi rend="italics">den</hi> 22 nov. <hi rend="italics">19..</hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.2" n="2">
               <hi rend="italics">a/b S.S. …</hi>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.a"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.3" n="3">*[S]* [<hi rend="italics">Figuren aan boord van het stoomschip Koningin der Nederlanden</hi>] <graphic url="ii044"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.4" n="4">Beste Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.5" n="5">Midden in de Indische oceaan, halfweg tusschen Aden en Ceylon,<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.1"/> dus een fatsoenlijk eindje weg, en waarachtig als je uit ’t venster kijkt van deze reading room en je ziet dat blauwgrijze water en die heel gewone hollandsche <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> luchten dan weet je dat je dat al lang gezien hebt, en waar? Wel, de Zuiderzee,  <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.2"/> doodgewoon, hetzelfde kalme zeetje met aan de horizont het eiland Urk.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.3"/> Behalve dat je <hi rend="italics">dat</hi> dan niet ziet is het hier ongeveer precies hetzelfde. ’t Is waar: als je op de thermometer kijkt staat die – ’t is nu ½ 11 ’s ochtends – op 85° Fahrenheit,<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.4"/> maar erg warm is ’t toch niet.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">Over 10 dagen zijn wij “er” dan. Ik ben wel benieuwd maar ik maak mij steeds minder illusies, tenminste niet over de Hollanders daar. Het zijn hier op de boot wel allemaal beste brave menschen, maar zoo Hollandsch! Namelijk wel degelijk en flink, maar zoo weinig aan gedaan om <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> het eenigszins aangenaam te maken. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers037">Duchatel</rs>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.5"/> is nog steeds hun ideaal en iets anders weten zij niet eens dat bestaat, schijnt het. Het is wel iets nieuws om met een honderd menschen die je absoluut niet kent, weken lang samen te moeten zijn, hier.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.6"/> Mijn hut is in alle geval heerlijk!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">Je ziet daar gemoedelijk de zon opgaan alsof dat altijd zoo gewoon was geweest. Zes uur op, is niets, heel eenvoudig! Het gekste is dat ik nog niets gelezen heb in die halve bibliotheek die ik heb meegenomen, denkend dat ik onderweg niets anders zou doen dan lezen!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.9" n="9" rend="indent">Ik leen ze uit, daar zijn ze best voor.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.10" n="10" rend="indent">
               <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r4" n="4"/> Wat je hier mist, zijn niet de kranten. Maar dat nooit iemand je een brief brengt, dat je van niemand iets hoort, je wist het wel vooruit maar ’t is toch wel een klein beetje saai ––––– </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.11" n="11" rend="indent">De Heer <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Reinhold</rs>, de vriend v. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs>, is nog steeds een sieraad van de boot!<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.7"/> Wel de geschikste zoowat, het is werkelijk een aardige jongen. Well my dear, I hope you are all right. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.12" n="12" rend="indent">Vele groeten aan   <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">Jos</rs>.<ptr type="note" target="#note.orig.nl.8"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.13" n="13">Yours always</p>
            <p xml:id="p.orig.nl.14" n="14">Isaac</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
            <pb xml:id="pb.tr.en.1"
                corresp="#pb.orig.nl.1"
                f="1r"
                facs="#z1r1"
                n="1"/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.1" corresp="#p.orig.nl.1" n="1">Tuesday <hi rend="italics">den</hi> 22 Nov. <hi rend="italics">19..</hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.2" corresp="#p.orig.nl.2" n="2">
               <hi rend="italics">a/b S.S. …</hi>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.a"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.3" corresp="#p.orig.nl.3" n="3">*[S]* [<hi rend="italics">Figures Aboard the Steamship Koningin der Nederlanden</hi>] <graphic url="ii044"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.4" corresp="#p.orig.nl.4" n="4">Dear Jo,</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.5" corresp="#p.orig.nl.5" n="5">In the middle of the Indian Ocean, halfway between Aden and Ceylon,<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.1"/> so a decent distance away, and truly if you look out of the window of this reading room and you see that blue grey water and these very ordinary Dutch <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v2" n="2"/> skies then you know that you’ve seen that for a long time, and where? Well, nowhere but the Zuiderzee,<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.2"/> the same calm little sea with the island of Urk on the horizon.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.3"/> Except that you don’t see <hi rend="italics">that</hi>, it’s almost exactly the same here. It’s true: if you look at the thermometer it’s reading – it’s now half past 10 in the morning – 85° Fahrenheit,<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.4"/> but it’s not actually very hot.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.6" corresp="#p.orig.nl.6" n="6" rend="indent">In 10 days we shall be ‘there’. I’m curious but I have ever fewer illusions, at least not about the Hollanders there. Here on the boat they are all good, decent people, but <hi rend="italics">so</hi> Dutch! That’s to say, respectable and stalwart, but have done so little about it to make it <pb f="1v" facs="#z1v3" n="3"/> in any way congenial. </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.7" corresp="#p.orig.nl.7" n="7" rend="indent">
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers037">Duchatel</rs>
               <ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.5"/> is still their ideal and it seems that they don’t know that anything else exists. It’s certainly something new to sit with a hundred people you absolutely don’t know, to have to sit together here for weeks.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.6"/> At least my cabin is delightful!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.8" corresp="#p.orig.nl.8" n="8" rend="indent">Pleasantly you see there the sun rise as if that had always been so ordinary. Six o’clock up, is nothing, very simple! The funniest thing is that I still haven’t read anything in the half a library I’ve brought with me, thinking that I’d do nothing but read on the journey!</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.9" corresp="#p.orig.nl.9" n="9" rend="indent">I lend them out, they’re good for that.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.10"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.10"
               n="10"
               rend="indent">
               <pb f="1r" facs="#z1r4" n="4"/> It’s not the papers you miss here. It’s that nobody ever brings you a letter, that you don’t hear from anyone, you knew it beforehand, but it really is a little bit dull ––––– </p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.11"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.11"
               n="11"
               rend="indent">Mr <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Reinhold</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs>’s friend, is still a jewel of the boat!<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.7"/> The most decent chap, he’s really a nice young man. Well my dear, I hope you are all right.</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.12"
               corresp="#p.orig.nl.12"
               n="12"
               rend="indent">Best wishes to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">Jos</rs>.<ptr type="note" target="#note.tr.en.8"/>
            </p>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.13" corresp="#p.orig.nl.13" n="13">Yours always</p>
            <p xml:id="p.tr.en.14" corresp="#p.orig.nl.14" n="14">Isaac</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note xml:id="note.d425e15729" type="dating">
            <p>Briefhoofd ‘22 nov’. Israëls’ reis naar Indonesië vond plaats in de herfst van 1921. Voorgedrukt briefpapier: ‘<hi rend="blockletter">stoomvaart maatschappij nederland</hi>’. Voorgedrukt staan: ‘den’, ‘19’ en ‘a/b S.S.’ Israëls vulde het jaar en de naam van het schip niet in. Het SS Koningin der Nederlanden was op 29 oktober uit Amsterdam vertrokken, aldus een bericht in <hi rend="italics">Scheepvaart</hi>, 31 oktober 1921, en arriveerde in Batavia op 2 december, aldus <hi rend="italics">De Locomotief</hi>, 2 december 1921.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="typednotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note xml:id="note.d425e15947" type="dating">
            <p>Letter headed ‘22 Nov’. Israëls’s journey to Indonesia took place in the autumn of 1921. Headed writing paper: ‘<hi rend="blockletter">stoomvaart maatschappij nederland</hi>’. Printed ‘den’, ‘19’ and ‘a/b S.S.’ Israëls did not fill in the year or the name of the ship. The <hi rend="italics">SS Koningin der Nederlanden</hi> sailed from Amsterdam on 29 October, according to an entry in <hi rend="italics">Scheepvaart</hi>, 31 October 192, and arrived in Batavia on 2 December, according to <hi rend="italics">De Locomotief</hi>, 2 December 1921.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.orig.nl.1">
            <p>Israëls zou op Java de steden Batavia (Jakarta), Jogjakarta en Solo (Surakarta) bezoeken. Ook ging hij naar het nabijgelegen eiland Bali.</p>
            <p>Elf dagen eerder, eveneens aan boord van het schip maar toen nog in de buurt van Port Said, schreef Israëls een brief aan <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers013">Augusta Maria Witsen-Schorr</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers129">Willem Witsen</rs>, met daarin de fraaie <hi rend="italics">one-liner</hi>: ‘De menschen zijn net als koekjes, als zij lang op elkaar geklit zijn bederven zij.’ <hi rend="italics">KBH</hi> 75 C 51; 11 november 1921.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.orig.nl.2">
            <p>De Zuiderzee stond toen nog in open verbinding met de zee; thans het IJsselmeer en Markermeer.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="3" xml:id="note.orig.nl.3">
            <p>Het vissersdorp Urk, gelegen aan de oostkant van het water.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="4" xml:id="note.orig.nl.4">
            <p>85° Fahrenheit is 29,4° Celsius.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="5" xml:id="note.orig.nl.5">
            <p>Waarschijnlijk een toespeling op <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers037">Fredericus Jacobus van Rossum du Chattel</rs>, de Nederlandse schilder, aquarellist en etser die landschappen en watergezichten maakte. Hij wordt gerekend tot de tweede generatie van de Haagse School. Zijn vader was de genreschilder <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers066">Jan Hendrik van Rossum du Chattel</rs>.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="6" xml:id="note.orig.nl.6">
            <p>De duur van de overtocht was zo’n vier weken. De schepen van de Stoomvaart Maatschappij Nederland (<hi rend="italics">SMN</hi>) deden onder meer in Italië de havenstad Genua aan.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="7" xml:id="note.orig.nl.7">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincents</rs> leeftijdgenoot <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Thomas (‘Tom’) Reinhold</rs>, de zoon van Jo’s vriendin <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers054">IJsbrandina (‘Dien’) Sophia Reinhold-Brandligt</rs>. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers054">Dien</rs> en haar man, de ingenieur <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers053">Huibert Reinhold</rs>, woonden omstreeks 1896 in Bussum. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Tom</rs>, die toen allebei zes jaar waren, speelden met elkaar. Later ging <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> tijdens vakanties bij hen logeren in Haarlem. <hi rend="italics">Dagboek Vincent</hi>, 6 november 1933.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Tom</rs> had geologie gestudeerd en was in 1915 in Bazel gepromoveerd – hij specialiseerde zich in het fotograferen in diepe boorgaten. In 1925, vier jaar na zijn ontmoeting met Israëls, zou hij trouwen. Omstreeks 1930 onderzocht hij fossiele diatomeeën in Indonesië en Belgisch Afrika. Zie zijn necrologie, geschreven door H.D.M. Burck in <hi rend="italics">Jaarboek Vereeniging Haerlem</hi>. Haarlem 1955, p. 26-27.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="8" xml:id="note.orig.nl.8">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> en <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">Josina</rs> woonden inmiddels op de Alexander Boersstraat 13 in Amsterdam, ongeveer een kilometer van Jo aan de Koninginneweg 77 vandaan.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="notes" xml:lang="en">
         <note n="1" xml:id="note.tr.en.1">
            <p>Israëls would visit Batavia (Jakarta), Jogjakarta and Solo (Surakarta) on Java. He also went to the neighbouring island of Bali.</p>
            <p>Eleven days earlier, likewise aboard the ship, but then still near Port Said, Israëls wrote a letter to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers013">Augusta Maria Witsen-Schorr</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers129">Willem Witsen</rs>, with the great one-liner: ‘People are just like biscuits, if they stick together for a long time they go stale.’ <hi rend="italics">KBH</hi> 75 C 51; 11 November 1921.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="2" xml:id="note.tr.en.2">
            <p>The Zuiderzee was then still open to the sea; nowadays it is the IJsselmeer and Markermeer.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="3" xml:id="note.tr.en.3">
            <p>The fishing village of Urk, on the east side of the water.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="4" xml:id="note.tr.en.4">
            <p>85° Fahrenheit is 29.4° Celsius.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="5" xml:id="note.tr.en.5">
            <p>Probably an allusion to <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers037">Fredericus Jacobus van Rossum du Chattel</rs>, a Dutch painter, watercolourist and etcher who made landscapes and views of water. He is reckoned to be one of the second generation of the Hague School. His father was the genre painter <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers066">Jan Hendrik van Rossum du Chattel</rs>.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="6" xml:id="note.tr.en.6">
            <p>The voyage took about four weeks. In Italy the Stoomvaart Maatschappij Nederland (<hi rend="italics">SMN</hi>) vessels called into the port of Genoa, among others.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="7" xml:id="note.tr.en.7">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs>’s contemporary <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Thomas (‘Tom’) Reinhold</rs>, the son of Jo’s friend <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers054">IJsbrandina (‘Dien’) Sophia Reinhold-Brandligt</rs>. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers054">Dien</rs> and her husband, the engineer <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers053">Huibert Reinhold</rs>, lived in Bussum around 1896. <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Tom</rs>, who were both six at the time, played together. Later <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> used to stay with them in Haarlem during the holidays. <hi rend="italics">Vincent’s Diary</hi>, 6 November 1933.</p>
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers124">Tom</rs> had studied geology and had gained his doctorate in Basel in 1915 – he specialized in photographing deep boreholes. He got married in 1925, four years after Israëls met him. Around 1930 he was researching fossil diatoms in Indonesia and Belgian Africa. See his obituary, written by H.D.M. Burck in <hi rend="italics">Jaarboek Vereeniging Haerlem</hi>. Haarlem 1955, pp. 26-27.</p>
         </note>
         <note n="8" xml:id="note.tr.en.8">
            <p>
               <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers128">Vincent</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="bio.xml#pers078">Josina</rs> were meanwhile living at 13 Alexander Boersstraat in Amsterdam, about a kilometre from Jo at 77 Koninginneweg. </p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="langnotes" xml:lang="nl">
         <note n="a" xml:id="note.orig.nl.a">
            <p>Aan boord [van het] stoomschip.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listAnnotation type="langnotes" xml:lang="en">
         <note n="a" xml:id="note.tr.en.a">
            <p>Aboard [the] steamship.</p>
         </note>
      </listAnnotation>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
